<?xml version="1.0"?>

<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<info>
		<title>Experiment Player</title>
		<subtitle>A tool for analyzing experiments...</subtitle>

		<author>
			<personname><firstname>Jens</firstname> <surname>Lammert</surname></personname>
			<email>jens.lammert@st.ovgu.de</email>
		</author>
		<copyright>
			<year>2012</year><holder>Otto-von-Guericke Universität Magdeburg</holder>
		</copyright>

		<abstract><para>
			The following document is an overview of various experiment-player features.			
		</para></abstract>
		
		<address>
			<uri>
				<link xlink:href="https://github.com/rhaberkorn/experiment-player">https://github.com/rhaberkorn/experiment-player</link></uri>
		</address>
	</info>

	<chapter>
		<title>Installation</title>
		<section>
			<title>Linux</title>
			<para>
				To install the experiment-player on a Linux based operation system
				the sources have to be downloaded from the 
				<link xlink:href="https://github.com/rhaberkorn/experiment-player/downloads">git-repository download page</link>.
				After that follow the instruction given by the <filename>INSTALL</filename> file.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Windows</title>
			<para>
				To install the experiment-player on a Windows operation system a ZIP-file
				can be downloaded from the
				<link xlink:href="https://github.com/rhaberkorn/experiment-player/downloads">git-repository download page</link>.
				It contains all nessessary binaries to run the experiment-player except 
				of the GTK+ widget toolkit. GTK+ 2.24.10 will also be needed to run the experiment-player on 
				Windows. The Installer and instructions can be downloaded from the GTK homepage.
				After installing GTK unzip the ZIP-file in any directory and excecute 
				experiment-player.exe to run the experiment-player.
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>First Steps</title>
		<para>
			After starting the experiment-player video-files and transcripts can be
			loaded. To open files first choose a directory in menue QuickOpen entry 
			Choose directory. Select any directory that contains the desired data. 
			If there are a XML-file and an AVI or MP4-file with an identical name the 
			data will bei listed under QuickOpen. For example <filename>20111117.xml</filename> and <filename>20111117.mp4</filename>.
			The last chosen directory will be saved as default value and will be
			selelected automaticly the at the next start.
		</para>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Transcript</title>
		<para>
			If the transcript is opened and a files was selected the transcript widget 
			shows the dialog between proband and wizard. The dialog monitor is divided 
			up into two seperate widgets so there can be different settings and fonts
			at each widget. Also it is possible to markup matches separate from each other.
			There two way to search matches: regular expressions and format files.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Regular Expressions</title>
			<para>
				For more information how to use regular expressions have a look at
				<link xlink:href="http://developer.gnome.org/glib/stable/glib-Perl-compatible-regular-expressions.html">glib documentation for Perl compatible regular expression</link>.
				Regular expressions are case-insensitive so both lower-case and upper-case character
				will match the same expression. Regular expression matches will be formated bold by default. 
				Captures are not be supported.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Format Expression</title>
			<para>
				By default a search term will be regarded as regular expression. If the
				markup toggle is activated the input expression will be regarded as 
				format expression which is a combination of regular expression and Pango mark up. 
				That means if the regular expression matchs at the text the markup 
				expressions will apply.
				For more information refer to the <link xlink:href="http://developer.gnome.org/pango/stable/PangoMarkupFormat.html">Pango Markup documentation.</link>.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Format Files</title>
			<para>
				Format files are collection of multiple format expressions. At first there
				has to be selected a quick open directory in menue Format entry Choose Directory. 
				After that all available format files in the selected directory will be listed
				under menue Formats. To create an own format file care the following:
				<itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
					<listitem>
						<para>Each line will regarded as a single mark up statement.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Leading whitespace characters will be ignored.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>A line beginning with '<filename>#</filename>' will be ignored complete.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Only whole lines can be ignored.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The format file has to save as a FMT-file (<filename>*.fmt</filename>).
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Incorrect lines will cause an error message.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				Let be the whole text referring to a single time stamp a text fragment.
				For each text fragment each format expression in the format file will be 
				iterated and the associated regular expression will matched. 
				For each match all associated mark ups will apply cumulatively at the 
				matching text.
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Config File</title>
		<para>
			The config file is located in the users default directory where each config 
			files are. By editing the config-file default keys which can not changed via 
			gui can set. More details about the structure of the config file can be 
			found in the
			<link xlink:href="developer.gnome.org/glib/unstable/glib-Key-value-file-parser.html">glib documentation</link>.
			
			The following table shows all additional keys :
			
			<table border="1">
				<thead border="1">
					<tr>
						<td>Key</td>
						<td>Description</td>
					</tr>
				</thead>
				<tbody border="1">
					<tr>
						<td><filename>Default-Format-Font</filename></td>
						<td>For detailed information follow <link xlink:href="http://developer.gnome.org/pango/stable/pango-Fonts.html#pango-font-description-from-string">pango font description</link></td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><filename>Default-Format-Text-Color</filename></td>
						<td>An RGB color specification such as '#00FF00' or a color name such as 'red'</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td><filename>Default-Format-BG-Color</filename></td>
						<td>An RGB color specification such as '#00FF00' or a color name such as 'red'</td>
					</tr>
				</tbody>
			</table>
		</para>
	</chapter>
</book>
